ok i'm going to talk about psycho brought because i think
his work really was the start of science
people think that science to so started long time ago with the greeks and
maybe with the arabs there but in actual fact science started with this man
and why do i say that
well let's look at the instruments that he used to observe the planets
he was the first person to really plot accurately
how the planets moved in the heavens
and just look the squid it he skill
that the people who made this separated had let's blow it up
this absolutely beautiful engraving
that was required to make these measurements which are very very difficult without telescopes really ok
there you can see that very accurate measurements of angles were made
at that time by tyco brought ok
and here
are some of his nose
now
it turns out that he died
after the name many of these measurements
and his technician nice bose was
kepler
and this is very fortunate because kepler was a brilliant
mathematician as well
and he
took all measurements of tyco brought che
and
he had to calculate very carefully
the orbits of the planets this is extremely difficulty in fact
he
made his own log tables you know computers and calculators
they used a lot tables to do e very complex mathematics particularly
division was extremely difficult
and he these written out in these what are called rudolf find tables
and the key
but i think that he discovers
was extremely important and here we see some of the original ideas
about the motions of the planets and the particular one that was most important was this one
which is the orbit of mars
and we see that the orbits of mars is not a circle
it's actually an ellipse us and the sum
is one focus
this
was the moment
when science started
when people making measurements
and carefully studied what those measurements meant
and as you know in those days before galileo
and copernicus people thought that the sum went round the earth
in fact common sense suggested as
in the morning it over here
in the evening as over their common sense suggests that the sum goes around the earth
but commonsense can be misleading
science's own commonsense
it looks behind the details to look more deeply into walls seems to be happening tries to find some evidence now
the evidence here indicated that it was actually earth
which circling round some
and that was known people like christian hoy guns very
famous
scientists in fact some people would say that he was the first
physical scientists soul and basically theoretical physicist
because he wrote the first equation
and in fact in a in
in holland in the netherlands
they put toy guns
banknotes
you'll find that in most countries scientists on banknotes in fact
in britain we have faraday
and we have darwin
and their here in the netherlands we have toy guns and if you go to ross figure austria
you harsher earlier
it's curious that in america they have politicians on banknotes
he suggests something different from the rest of the world
however
hoynes was really
a physicist and here are some of his drawings he was the first person to propose the
wave theory of light
but he also knew a a lot of mathematics and he also understood and differentiation
here are his drawings of the waves of light coming out from a candle and
here are some of the drawings from his books
and he he as i understood it actually he took the first paint on a spring watch
of clockwork watch
so he is really
the father
of this watch which people pay a lot of money flaw
compared to this fantastic large which which is a
sort of really an amazing e sort of culmination of technology
which is there any 44 anymore
but in fact this one more accurate than this one
now
hoynes knew the centre of pure roll force law
and the also new or something about satins motions and realize that saturn's rings could not be solid
and so he's really one of the first theoretical physicists if not the first
and he actually understood
this particular equation
in calculus
however
what happened then
was that robert hook
who it was very really a genius but not very good mathematician
wrote to newton
and
in the letter said you do you think that an inverse square law
would explain
the motions of the planets in particular
the fact that the orbits of mars was an ellipse
with some at its center
now the inverse square law is an interesting one it applies to light
as you move away from say with the torch
the inverse square law indicates that the intensity
of the light falling on the surface rule
reduce by the square of the distance r that you're travelling away from it
now you can
actually then solve these problems as most of us know
and he and use such things as
calculus and integration
but let's look at his integration this is from
his
book principia
and what we see is as a curve
and he wants to know
the area of this curve
and if we look at what he says saying we have the curve k
a b l and then an aide see that those wrecked tangles put those rectangles
on the inside of the curve
and it put another set of rectangles
which are on the outside of the curve right
and now what he says is i say that the ultimate ratios
which the inscribed figure eight kb l eat
then di
di this is almost like a sort of going to the optician
or the circumscribe figure ai little a l b n c n-d
easy and
the curve linear figure
ai may be di will have
to and one another
our ratios of equality
so what does he actually say in modern english
he says that as rectangles become thinner
the area of the interaction angles and the area of the outer rectangles will converge on the
area under the curve
and if we look back at these images
we see that here are the inscribed rectangles
and there he is circumscribed rectangles and as we narrow the e the rectangular ways
we get closer and closer
to the area of
that
curve
that curve
now that was not nearly
because archimedes the great the first great mathematician actually knew that
but if you look in cricket here
you find
that is written in words
in fact is very interesting
there is no physically equations in principia
it's all in words
you indeed developed
a form of calculus
and he of explain the motions of the planets and therefore
this
period the lysate started with cycle briars measurements of the orbits of the planets
then kepler
doing very accurate study
of the orbits showing that they are this sort of ellipses and not circles and other some
is the focus of one of these on the earth moves round it
it could use models other looking at
and then hook
suggesting to newton that an inverse square law would explain it
and you mean
the an outstanding mathematician showing that the inverse square law did explain
the motions of the planets
and that is the origin
of
what we now call classical mechanics on you mechanics